<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>
<?rfc toc='yes'?>
<?rfc compact='yes'?>
<?rfc subcompact='no'?>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     xml:lang="en"
     ipr="trust200902"
     submissionType="IETF"
     consensus="true"
     category="std"
     docName="draft-ietf-tsvwg-sctp-zero-checksum-09-to-be"
     version="3">

<front>
<title abbrev='Zero Checksum for SCTP'>
Zero Checksum for the Stream Control Transmission Protocol
</title>
<seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-tsvwg-sctp-zero-checksum-09-to-be"/>

<author initials="M." surname="Tüxen" fullname="Michael Tüxen">
  <organization abbrev='Münster Univ. of Appl. Sciences'>
                Münster University of Applied Sciences</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
        <street>Stegerwaldstrasse 39</street>
        <city>48565 Steinfurt</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
    </postal>
    <email>tuexen@fh-muenster.de</email>
  </address>
</author>

<author initials='V.' surname='Boivie' fullname='Victor Boivie'>
  <organization>Google</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street>Kungsbron 2</street>
      <city>Stockholm</city>
      <code>11122</code>
      <country>Sweden</country>
    </postal>
    <email>boivie@google.com</email>
  </address>
</author>

<author initials='F.' surname='Castelli' fullname='Florent Castelli'>
  <organization>Google</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street>Kungsbron 2</street>
      <city>Stockholm</city>
      <code>11122</code>
      <country>Sweden</country>
    </postal>
    <email>orphis@google.com</email>
  </address>
</author>

<author initials="R." surname="Jesup" fullname="Randell Jesup">
<organization abbrev='Mozilla'>
              Mozilla Corporation</organization>
<address>
    <postal>
        <street>1835 Horse Shoe Trl</street>
        <city>Malvern</city>
        <region>PA</region>
        <code>19355</code>
        <country>US</country>
    </postal>
    <email>randell-ietf@jesup.org</email>
</address>
</author>

<date />

<abstract>
<t>The Stream Control Transmission Protocol (SCTP) uses a 32-bit checksum in
the common header of each packet to provide some level of data integrity.
If another method used by SCTP provides already the same or a higher level of
data integrity, computing this checksum does not provide any additional
protection, but does consume computing resources.</t>
<t>This document provides a simple extension to SCTP allowing to save these
computing resources by using zero as the checksum in a backwards compatible
way.
It also defines how this feature can be used when SCTP packets are encapsulated
in Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS) packets.</t>
</abstract>
</front>

<middle>
<section>
<name>Introduction</name>
<t>SCTP as specified in <xref target="RFC9260"/> uses a CRC32c checksum to
provide some level of data integrity.
When using, for example, Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS) as the
lower layer for SCTP as specified in <xref target="RFC8261"/>, using the CRC32c
checksum does not provide any additional protection over the one already
provided by DTLS.
However, computing the CRC32c checksum  at the sender and receiver side does
consume computational resources for no benefit.
This is particularly important for end points that are computational-limited
and use SCTP encapsulated in DTLS.</t>
<t>The extension described in this document allows an SCTP end point to declare
that it accepts SCTP packets with a checksum of zero when using a specific
alternate error detection method.
This declaration happens during the setup of the SCTP association and allows
end points supporting this extension to be interoperable with end points not
supporting the extension described in this document.
To provide this backwards compatibility, end points using this extension still
need to implement the CRC32c checksum algorithm.</t>
</section>

<section anchor='conventions'>
<name>Conventions</name>
<t>The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
"<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>",
"<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>",
"<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
"<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to
be interpreted as described in
BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when,
they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
</section>

<section anchor='alternate_error_detection_methods'>
<name>Alternate Error Detection Methods</name>
<t>SCTP uses a CRC32c checksum to provide some level of data integrity.
The CRC32c checksum is computed based on the SCTP common header and the chunks
contained in the packet.
In particular, the computation of the CRC32c checksum does not involve a pseudo
header for IPv4 or IPv6 like the computation of the TCP checksum, as specified
in <xref target='RFC9293'/>, or the UDP checksum, as specified in
<xref target='RFC0768'/>.</t>
<t>Zero is a valid result of the CRC32c checksum algorithm.
For example, the following figure depicts an SCTP packet containing a minimal
INIT chunk with a correct CRC32c checksum of zero.</t>
<figure>
<name>SCTP Packet with a correct CRC32c checksum of zero</name>
<artwork align='center'>
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Source Port Number = 5001   |Destination Port Number = 5001 |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                     Verification Tag = 0                      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                         Checksum = 0                          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Type = 1    |Chunk Flags = 0|       Chunk Length = 20       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                   Initiate Tag = 0xFCB75CCA                   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       Advertised Receiver Window Credit (a_rwnd) = 1500       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|Number of Outbound Streams = 1 | Number of Inbound Streams = 1 |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                        Initial TSN = 0                        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
</figure>

<t>Using SCTP in combination with other mechanisms or protocol extensions might
provide an equal or better level of data integrity protection than the one
provided by using the CRC32c checksum algorithm.
When using such alternate error detection methods, the SCTP common header
containing the 32-bit checksum field might or might not be visible to
middleboxes on the paths between the two end points.</t>
<t>Alternate error detection methods have two requirements:</t>
<ol>
<li><t>An alternate error detection method <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> provide an equal
or better level of data integrity than the one provided by using the CRC32c
checksum algorithm.
This <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> only apply to packets satisfying some method specific
constraints.</t></li>
<li><t>Using an alternate error detection method <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>
result in a path failure for more than two retransmission timeouts (RTO)
due to middleboxes on the path expecting correct CRC32c checksums.</t></li>
</ol>
<t>To fulfill the second requirement, alternate error detection methods
<bcp14>MAY</bcp14> use a heuristic to detect the existence of such middleboxes
and use correct CRC32c checksums on these affected paths.</t>
<t>One example fulfilling the first requirement is using DTLS as the lower layer
of SCTP as specified in <xref target="RFC8261"/>.
Another example is using SCTP Authentication as specified in
<xref target="RFC4895"/>.
Of course, this only applies to all SCTP packets having an AUTH chunk as its
first chunk.
However, using SCTP Authentication without any heuristic does not fulfill the
second requirement.
Since using DTLS as the lower layer of SCTP as specified in
<xref target="RFC8261"/> also fulfills the second requirement, it can be used
as an alternate error detection method
(see <xref target="edm_sctp_over_dtls"/>).</t>
<t>If an alternate error detection method is available, the computation of the
CRC32c checksum consumes computational resources without providing any benefit.
To avoid this, an SCTP end point could be willing to accept SCTP packets with
an incorrect CRC32c checksum value of zero in addition to SCTP packets with
correct CRC32c checksum values.</t>
<t>Because zero is a valid result of the CRC32c checksum algorithm, a receiver
of an SCTP packet containing a checksum value of zero cannot determine whether
the sender included an incorrect CRC32c checksum of zero to reduce the CPU cost
or the result of the CRC32c checksum computation was actually zero.
However, if the receiver is willing to use an alternate error detection method,
this ambiguity is irrelevant, since the receiver is fine with not using the
CRC32c checksum to protect incoming packets.</t>
</section>

<section>
<name>A New Chunk Parameter</name>
<t>The Zero Checksum Acceptable Chunk Parameter is defined by the
following figure.</t>
<figure>
<name>Zero Checksum Acceptable Chunk Parameter</name>
<artwork align="center">
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Type = 0x8001 (suggested)   |          Length = 8           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|           Error Detection Method Identifier (EDMID)           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
</figure>
<dl newline="true">
<dt>Type: 16 bits (unsigned integer)</dt>
<dd>
<t>This field holds the IANA defined parameter type for the
"Zero Checksum Acceptable" chunk parameter.
IANA is requested to assign the value 32769 (0x8001) (suggested) for this
parameter type.</t>
</dd>
<dt>Length: 16 bits (unsigned integer)</dt>
<dd>
<t>This field holds the length in bytes of the chunk parameter;
the value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 8.</t>
</dd>
<dt>Error Detection Method Identifier (EDMID): 32 bits (unsigned integer)</dt>
<dd>
<t>An IANA registered value specifying the alternate error detection method
the sender of this parameter is willing to use for received packets.</t>
</dd>
</dl>
<t>All transported integer numbers are in "network byte order" a.k.a.,
Big Endian.</t>
<t>The Zero Checksum Acceptable Chunk Parameter <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> appear
in INIT and INIT ACK chunks and <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> appear in any other
chunk.
The Parameter <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> appear more than once in any chunk.</t>
<t>If an end point not supporting the extension described in this document
receives this parameter in an INIT or INIT ACK chunk, it is
<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14> to skip this parameter and continue to process further
parameters in the chunk.
This behavior is specified by <xref target="RFC9260"/> because the highest-order
two bits of the Type are '10'.</t>
</section>

<section>
<name>Procedures</name>

<section>
<name>Declaration of Feature Support</name>
<t>An end point willing to accept SCTP packets with an incorrect checksum of
zero <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include the Zero Checksum Acceptable Chunk Parameter
indicating the alternate error detection method it is willing to use in the
INIT or INIT ACK chunk it sends.</t>
<t>An SCTP implementation <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> also require the upper layer to
indicate that it is fine to use a specific alternate error detection method
for accepting SCTP packets with an incorrect CRC32c checksum value of zero.</t>
</section>

<section anchor='sender_side_considerations'>
<name>Sender Side Considerations</name>
<t>An SCTP end point cannot just use an incorrect CRC32c checksum value of zero
for all SCTP packets it sends.
The following restrictions apply:</t>
<ol>
<li><t>If an end point has not received an INIT or INIT ACK chunk containing a
Zero Checksum Acceptable Chunk Parameter indicating an alternate error detection
method it supports from its peer during the association setup,
it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use a correct CRC32c checksum.
In particular, when an end point</t>
<ol type='%c.'>
<li><t>sends a packet containing an INIT chunk, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include
a correct CRC32c checksum in the packet containing the INIT chunk.</t></li>
<li><t>responds to an "Out of the Blue" (OOTB) SCTP packet, it
<bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include a correct CRC32c checksum in the response
packet.</t></li>
</ol></li>
<li><t>When an end point sends a packet containing a COOKIE ECHO chunk, it
<bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include a correct CRC32c checksum in the packet containing
the COOKIE ECHO chunk.</t></li>
<li><t>When an end point supports the dynamic address reconfiguration specified
in <xref target='RFC5061'/> and sends a packet containing an ASCONF chunk, it
<bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include a correct CRC32c checksum in the packet containing
the ASCONF chunk.</t></li>
<li><t>Alternate error detection methods might have some additional conditions
requiring that the sender <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include a correct CRC32c checksum
in the packet.</t></li>
</ol>
<t>The first restriction allows backwards compatibility, and the second and
third restrictions allow a simpler implementation of the extension defined in
this document.
The last restriction covers alternate error detection method specific
constraints.</t>
<t>An SCTP end point <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> only send packets with an incorrect
checksum of zero, if the upper layer allowed the use of the alternate error
detection method that was announced by the peer.</t>
<t>If none of the above restrictions apply, an end point <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>
use zero as the checksum when sending an SCTP packet.</t>
</section>

<section>
<name>Receiver Side Considerations</name>
<t>If an end point has sent the Zero Checksum Acceptable Chunk Parameter
indicating the support of an alternate error detection method in an INIT or
INIT ACK chunk, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> accept SCTP packets fulfilling the
requirements of the announced alternate error detection method using
an incorrect checksum value of zero in addition to SCTP packets containing the
correct CRC32c checksum value for this association.</t>
<t>In addition to processing OOTB packets with a correct CRC32c checksum as
specified in <xref target='RFC9260'/>, an SCTP implementation
<bcp14>MAY</bcp14> also process OOTB packets having an incorrect zero checksum.
Doing so might result in faster SCTP association failure detection.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor='edm_sctp_over_dtls'>
<name>Error Detection via SCTP over DTLS</name>
<t>Using SCTP over DTLS as specified in <xref target="RFC8261"/> provides
a stronger error detection method than using the CRC32c checksum algorithm.
Since middleboxes will not observe the unencrypted SCTP packet, there is
no risk in interfering with using zero as an incorrect checksum.
There are no additional error detection method specific constraints on packets
when using DTLS encapsulation.</t>
<t>IANA is requested to assign the Error Detection Method Identifier
of 1 for this method.</t>
</section>

<section>
<name>Socket API Considerations</name>
<t>This section describes how the socket API defined in
<xref target='RFC6458'/> needs to be extended to provide a way for the
application to control the acceptance of a zero checksum.</t>
<t>A 'Socket API Considerations' section is contained in all SCTP related
specifications published after <xref target='RFC6458'/> describing an extension
for which implementations using the socket API as specified in
<xref target='RFC6458'/> would require some extension of the socket API.
Please note that this section is informational only.</t>
<t>A socket API implementation based on <xref target='RFC6458'/> is extended by
supporting one new write-only IPPROTO_SCTP-level socket option.</t>

<section>
<name>Set Accepting a Zero Checksum (SCTP_ACCEPT_ZERO_CHECKSUM)</name>
<t>This IPPROTO_SCTP-level socket option with the name SCTP_ACCEPT_ZERO_CHECKSUM
can be used to control the acceptance of a zero checksum.
It is a write-only socket option and applies only to future SCTP associations
on the socket.</t>
<t>This option expects an unsigned integer.
Possible values include:</t>
<dl>
<dt>SCTP_EDMID_NONE:</dt>
<dd><t>Disable the use of alternate error detection method.
This means that all SCTP packets being sent have a correct CRC32c checksum
value.</t></dd>
<dt>SCTP_EDMID_LOWER_LAYER_DTLS:</dt>
<dd><t>Use the alternate error detection method described in
<xref target='edm_sctp_over_dtls'/>.</t></dd>
</dl>
<t>An implementation might only send packets with an incorrect checksum of zero,
if the alternate error detection method announced by the peer is also enabled
locally via this socket option.</t>
<t>The default for this socket option is that the use of alternate error
detection methods is disabled.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<name>IANA Considerations</name>
<t>[NOTE to RFC-Editor: "RFCXXXX" is to be replaced by the RFC number you
assign this document.]</t>
<t>[NOTE to RFC-Editor: The suggested value for the parameter type is tentative
and to be confirmed by IANA.]</t>
<t>This document (RFCXXXX) is the reference for the registration described
in this section.</t>
<t>A new chunk parameter type has to be assigned by IANA.
This requires an additional line in the "Chunk Parameter Types" registry for
SCTP:</t>
<table>
<name>New entry in "Chunk Parameter Types" registry</name>
<thead>
<tr><th>ID Value</th>             <th>Chunk Parameter Type</th>                          <th>Reference</th></tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>32769 (suggested)</td>    <td>Zero Checksum Acceptable (0x8001 (suggested))</td> <td>[RFCXXXX]</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<t>Furthermore, IANA is requested to establish a new "Error Detection Method"
registry for SCTP.
<!-- This is what Magnus prefers. -->
The assignment of new error detection methods is done through the Specification
Required policy as defined in <xref target='RFC8126'/>.
<!-- Gorry currently prefers:
The assignment of new error detection methods is done through the IETF Review
policy as defined in <xref target='RFC8126'/>.
-->
Documentation for a new error detection method <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> contain the
following information:</t>
<ol>
<li><t>A name of an alternate error detection method.</t></li>
<li><t>A reference to a specification describing:</t>
<ol type='(%c)'>
<li><t>the alternate error detection method,</t></li>
<li><t>why the alternate error detection method provides an equal or better
level of data integrity protection than the one provided by using the CRC32c
checksum,</t></li>
<li><t>any alternate error detection method specific constraints referred to in
the fourth exception in <xref target='sender_side_considerations'/>, and</t></li>
<li><t>why using the alternate error detection method does not result in
path failures due to middleboxes expecting correct CRC32c checksums for more
than two RTOs.
In case the alternate error detection method uses a heuristic for detecting
such middleboxes, this heuristic needs to be described.</t></li>
</ol></li>
</ol>
<t>IANA is requested to use the following as the initial contents of the
registry:</t>
<table>
<name>Initial Contents of the "Error Detection Method" registry</name>
<thead>
<tr><th>ID Value</th>       <th>Error Detection Method</th> <th>Reference</th></tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr><td>0             </td> <td>Reserved</td>               <td>[RFCXXXX]</td></tr>
<tr><td>1             </td> <td>SCTP over DTLS</td>         <td>[RFCXXXX]</td></tr>
<tr><td>2 - 4294967295</td> <td>Unassigned</td>             <td>         </td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<t>A Designated Expert (DE) is expected to ascertain the existence of suitable
documentation (a specification) as described in <xref target='RFC8126'/> and to
verify that the document is permanently and publicly available.
Furthermore, the DE is expected to ensure that the above four points have been
addressed in an appropriate way.</t>
</section>

<section>
<name>Security Considerations</name>
<t>This document does not change the considerations given in
<xref target="RFC9260"/>.</t>
</section>
</middle>

<back>
<references>
<name>References</name>
<references>
<name>Normative References</name>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5061.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8261.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9260.xml"/>
</references>

<references>
<name>Informative References</name>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0768.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4895.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6458.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9293.xml"/>
</references>
</references>

<section numbered='false'>
<name>Acknowledgments</name>
<t>The authors wish to thank
<contact fullname="Gorry Fairhurst"/>,
<contact fullname="Mike Heard"/>,
<contact fullname="Peter Lei"/>,
<contact fullname="Nils Ohlmeier"/>,
<contact fullname="Claudio Porfiri"/>,
<contact fullname="Greg Skinner"/>,
<contact fullname="Timo Völker"/>, and
<contact fullname="Magnus Westerlund"/>
for their invaluable comments.</t>
</section>
</back>
</rfc>
